<TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
          <titleStmt>
            <title level="m" type="main">The Ruined Castle</title>
            <title level="m" type="sub"> a machine readable transcription</title>
            <author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q272537">Felicia Hemans</author>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Transcription and encoding</resp>
                <persName xml:id="sy">Susannah Young</persName>
            </respStmt>
          </titleStmt>
          <editionStmt>
            <edition>
                <date>2026</date>
            </edition>
          </editionStmt>

        <publicationStmt>
            <availability><p>Unpublished digital edition for MLIS portfolio. The text of the original item is in the public domain.</p></availability>
        </publicationStmt>

          <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                    <author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q272537">
                    <choice>
                    <orig>Felicia Dorothea Browne</orig>
                    <reg>Felicia Dorothea Hemans</reg>
                    </choice>
                    </author>
                    <title level="m" type="main">Poems</title>
                    <title level="a" type="main">The Ruined Castle</title>
                    <orgName xml:id="digitizer">Wikimedia Commons</orgName>
                    <imprint>
                        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                        <publisher>T. Cadell and W. Davies</publisher>
                        <printer>G. F. Harris</printer>
                        <date>1808</date>
                    </imprint>
                </monogr>
                <note type="project">
                Transcribed from digital images of the original.
                Digitized version available as scanned PDF via Wikimedia Commons.
                        <ptr type="url" target="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/86/1808_Poems_by_Felicia_Dorothea_Browne.pdf"/>
                </note>
            </biblStruct>

            <bibl>
                <author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q207858">Felicia Hemans</author>
                <title level="a" type="main">The Ruined Castle</title>
                <date xml:id="dat1" notBefore="1800" notAfter="1808" cert="medium">Between 1800 and 1808</date>
                <note type="project">
                    Poems in Hemans' 1808 volume were composed between ages 8 and 13, ranging from around 1800 to first publication in 1808.
                </note>
            </bibl>

          </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p>Encoded for portfolio demonstration using TEI P5</p>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p>Five poems were selected to represent differing attitudes toward history, monuments, and power in Romantic-era poetry.</p>
            </samplingDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text>
      <body>
        <lg type="poem">
          <head>The Ruined Castle</head>
          <l>Oh! let me sigh to think this ruin’d pile</l>
          <l>Was favour'd once with fortune's radiant smile;</l>
          <l>These moss-grown battlements, these ivy'd towers,</l>
          <l>Have seen prosperity's uncertain hours;</l>
          <l>Their heroes triumph'd in the scenes of war,</l>
          <l>While victory follow'd in her trophied car.</l>
          <l>Here, where I muse in meditation's arms,</l>
          <l>Perhaps the battle raged with loud alarms;</l>
          <l>Here glory's crimson banner waving spread,</l>
          <l>While laurel crowns entwin'd the victor's head;</l>
          <l>And here, perhaps, with many a plaintive tear,</l>
          <l>The mourner has bedew'd the soldier's bier.</l>
          <l>The scene of conquest pensive fancy draws,</l>
          <l>Where thousands fell, enthusiasts in their cause.</l>
          <l>Yon turret, moulder'd by the hand of time,</l>
          <l>Shaded by silver ash and spreading lime,</l>
          <l>Was once, perhaps, the hall of mirth and joy,</l>
          <l>Where warriors sought no longer to destroy;</l>
          <l>And where, perhaps, the hoary-headed sage,</l>
          <l>Would lead them o'er the animating page;</l>
          <l>Where history points to glorious ages fled,</l>
          <l>And tells the noble actions of the dead.</l>
          <l>Still fancy with a magic power recalls</l>
          <l>The time when trophies grac'd the lofty walls:</l>
          <l>When with enchanting spells the minstrel's art,</l>
          <l>Could soften and inspire the melting heart;</l>
          <l>Could raise the glowing elevated flame,</l>
          <l>And bid the youthful soldier pant for fame:</l>
          <l>While deeds of glory were the themes he sung,</l>
          <l>The pleasant harp in wild accordance rung.</l>
          <l>Ah! where is now the warrior's ardent fire?</l>
          <l>Where now the tuneful spirit of the lyre?</l>
          <l>The warrior sleeps; the minstrel's lay is still;</l>
          <l>No songs of triumph echo from the hill.</l>
          <l>Ah! yet the weeping muse shall love to sigh,</l>
          <l>And trace again thy fallen majesty;</l>
          <l>And still shall Fancy linger on the theme,</l>
          <l>While forms of heroes animate her dream.</l>

        </lg>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>